<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-18T15:43:40+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BEC lab</title><subtitle>Page of BEC lab</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The lab goes to AMPEE</title><link href="/blog/AMPEE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The lab goes to AMPEE" /><published>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/AMPEE</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/AMPEE/">&lt;p&gt;On September 29th, 2022, Elise, Lea, Nicolas, Sébastien and Thibault went to the 6th AMPEE. AMPEE is an initiative of the Royal Botanical Society of Belgium and Meise Botanic Garden.
Our PhD students all presented their latest results, while Nicolas was quietly drinking coffee. Collaborator of the lab Luca Borgato also gave a talk. Looking forward to next year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">6th Annual Meeting on Plant Ecology and Evolution</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC</title><link href="/blog/Floramac/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC" /><published>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Floramac</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Floramac/">&lt;p&gt;FloraMac is a 5 days congress on the Macaronesian flora. Every three years it takes place in a different location with this year edition on the island of La Gomera, Canary Islands. Macaronesia is a group of four archipelagos: the Azores, Madeira, the Canary Islands and Cape Verde. &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mouton&quot;&gt;Lea Mouton&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mirolo&quot;&gt;Sébastien Mirolo&lt;/a&gt; were invited to present their current project about Beta diversity across geographic scales and lineages and about island disharmony and the origin of the Macaronesian bryophyte community, respectively. They had the opportunity to meet great researchers and learn more about the flora of islands and oceanic islands theories. In addition, they have been enjoying the beautiful landscape of this magnificent Canarian island. Because of its rich biodiversity and its high endemism rate, La Gomera was awarded Biosphere Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An International symposium on the Macaronesian flora</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field course in Pyrenees</title><link href="/blog/Pyrenees/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field course in Pyrenees" /><published>2022-07-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Pyrenees</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Pyrenees/">&lt;p&gt;On July 3-13, 2022, students of the master in ecology and organisms biology (specialization in conservation biology) participated into a field course in Pyrenees (France and Spain) with &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/magain&quot;&gt;Nicolas Magain&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mouton&quot;&gt;Lea Mouton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Serusiaux&quot;&gt;Emmanuël Sérusiaux&lt;/a&gt;, Ludovic Sottiaux and Philippe Dury.
&lt;p&gt; We explored coexistence with big carnivorous animals such as wolves and bears, nature conservation and human impact on the landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the atlantic side in France to Bardenas in Aragon, students could observe so many organisms, including a lot of vultures and birds of prey, and relics from the Tertiary age such as  Ramonda myconi and carnivorous plants of the genus  Pinguicula).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few pictures are available on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CjhxGXejQ4v/&quot;&gt;Instagram page of the Faculty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Discovering nature, coexistence with bears and tropical relics</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pyrenees1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/pyrenees1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field course in Cevennes</title><link href="/blog/Cevennes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field course in Cevennes" /><published>2022-05-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Cevennes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Cevennes/">&lt;p&gt;On May 14-22, 2022, students of the master in ecology and organisms biology went to Cévennes (Lozère, France) for a field course in biogeography (&lt;a href=&quot;/members/Vanderpoorten&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alain Vanderpoorten&lt;/a&gt;) and plant systematics (&lt;a href=&quot;/members/magain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicolas Magain&lt;/a&gt;).

&lt;p&gt;Hosted in &quot;Camping de la cascade&quot; in Meyrueis, students enjoyed a perfect weather and discovered the landscapes of  Parc National des Cévennes.&lt;/p&gt;

&amp;lt;We studied the flora of very different landscapes, and discovered several endemic species, before doing some ecological modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some pictures can be found on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CisDKAljwVg/&quot;&gt;Instagram page of the Faculty.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ecological modelling and endemic species</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Cevennes8.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Cevennes8.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Antoine got a Marie Skłodowska-Curie postdoctoral fellowship!</title><link href="/blog/antoine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antoine got a Marie Skłodowska-Curie postdoctoral fellowship!" /><published>2022-03-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-03-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/antoine</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/antoine/">&lt;p&gt;Antoine Simon (post-doctoral fellow at UConn and BEC lab alumni) got awarded a Marie Skłodowska-Curie postdoctoral fellowship to work with Prof. Einar Timdal (Natural History Museum, University of Oslo) on genomic approaches applied to historical herbarium specimens. His project FRAME (Fungal Research in the Age of Museomic Exploration) will aim at generating informative genetic data from ancient lichen collections, providing a cost-effective and labor-saving strategy to integrate relevant museum collections in biodiversity research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Way to go Antoine! We are thrilled that we will continue collaborating with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Picture: Antoine posing on the southern New England tripoint marker, visibly thrilled to be simultaneously in Connecticut, Massachusetts and Rhode Island.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Great achievement for our former PhD student</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/antoine.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/antoine.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Collecting field trip in Parc National de Guadeloupe for Elise’s thesis</title><link href="/blog/guad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collecting field trip in Parc National de Guadeloupe for Elise’s thesis" /><published>2022-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/guad</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/guad/">&lt;p&gt;From January 18 to February 1st, as a research collaboration with the Parc National de Guadeloupe, Elise Lebreton (FRIA PhD Student), Nicolas Magain and Emmanuël Sérusiaux sampled lichens and leaves in Guadeloupe. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of organisms grow on the surface of leaves in tropical forests, including lichens, fungi, algae and bryophytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three main goals of the field trip were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- A taxonomic and phylogenetic revision of Gomphillaceae and Strigulaceae in Guadeloupe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Characterizing green algae within and outside of lichens at the surface of leaves from an ecological point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- A broader project of checklists of lichens from France&apos;s Overseas territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Even if recent sulphur emissions from the volcano seem to have harmed lichen communities, the field trip was a success, with many interesting specimens collected!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A lot of work for Elise in the lab now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A slideshow of pictures from the field trip can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciences.uliege.be/cms/c_8984836/fr/mission-de-recolte-en-guadeloupe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Website of the Faculté des Sciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Picture: Barthélémy Dessanges from the Parc National de Guadeloupe delivering the collecting permits to Elise and Nicolas.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Two weeks collecting lichens and leaves</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/barthelemy.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/barthelemy.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lucie got a FRIA PhD fellowship!</title><link href="/blog/lucie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lucie got a FRIA PhD fellowship!" /><published>2021-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/lucie</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/lucie/">&lt;p&gt;Lucie Lelotte got a FRIA PhD fellowship!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucie obtained a FRIA fellowship from the FNRS to pursue 4 years of doctoral research in our lab, in collaboration with NINA (Norwegian Institute for Nature Research, the acronym must work in Norwegian).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She will be working on the spatial ecology, habitat selection and conservation biology of reindeers in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to joining our team, Lucie obtained a Master in Organisms Biology and Ecology with a specialisation in conservation biology (the infamous BCBG master, the acronym works in French) from Université de Liège. Her master thesis was already dedicated to Norwegian reindeers, in collaboration with Bram Van Moorter from NINA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations Lucie!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">FRIA fellowhsip to work on spatial ecology, habitat selection and conservation biology of reindeers in Norway</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Lucie.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Lucie.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A video in French presenting the ULiège Herbarium</title><link href="/blog/herbariumvideo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A video in French presenting the ULiège Herbarium" /><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/herbariumvideo</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/herbariumvideo/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-the-web-page-the-video&quot;&gt;After the web page, the video!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fb.watch/913eRXBb-g/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A video&lt;/a&gt; that presents our herbarium&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This video was created with the Pôle Muséal team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Pôle muséal&quot; aims at creating synergies between the University&apos;s museums and collections, for research, teaching and the general public. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, a new full website will be available for our herbarium&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Strong synergies are being developed among University&apos;s collections</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/joubarbe.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/joubarbe.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The herbarium is highlighted on the new website of the University museums</title><link href="/blog/herbarium/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The herbarium is highlighted on the new website of the University museums" /><published>2021-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/herbarium</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/herbarium/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-new-page-highlighting-a-few-or-our-herbarium-collections&quot;&gt;A new page highlighting a few or our herbarium collections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now find a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.musees.uliege.be/cms/c_14639854/fr/musees-herbarium&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;presentation of our collections on the website of the &quot;Pôle muséal&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The herbarium is host to over 600 000 collections of plants, fungi and algae, including many types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &quot;Pôle muséal&quot; aims at creating synergies between the University&apos;s museums and collections, for research, teaching and the general public. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, a new full website will be available for our herbarium&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Strong synergies are being developed among University&apos;s collections</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/vanille.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/vanille.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field course in Romania</title><link href="/blog/romania/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field course in Romania" /><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/romania</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/romania/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;finally-back-to-the-field-in-romania-with-students&quot;&gt;Finally back to the field in Romania with students!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From September 5 to 16, 2021, students of the conservation biology master went to the Romanian Carpathian mountains and Transylvania to discover its outstanding fauna and flora.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked about this hotspot of biodiversity and how traditional agriculture including late mowing by hand and extensive grazing led to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also talked about coexisting with bears and wolves, met with farmers, and visited bogs and primary forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find a photo album on the Faculty of Sciences&apos; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?vanity=ULiegefacsciences&amp;amp;set=a.2928112107504102&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CUsBt5ys_Km/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Finally back to the field with students</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/romania.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/romania.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>