<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-19T13:08:21+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BEC lab</title><subtitle>Page of BEC lab</subtitle><entry><title type="html">New field course in the new ESEM National Park</title><link href="/blog/Viroin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New field course in the new ESEM National Park" /><published>2023-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Viroin</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Viroin/">&lt;p&gt;From May 2 to May 5, 2023, students from the Master in Organisms Biology and Ecology, specializing in Nature Conservation and Biodiversity Management went to Viroinval for our field course in naturalism. The students were welcomed at the Ecosite of Vierves-sur-Viroin by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cercles-naturalistes.be/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Naturalist Circles of Belgium (CNB)&lt;/a&gt;. They had the opportunity to study a diverse local fauna and flora between Fagne, Calestienne and Ardenne, within the new National Park “Entre Sambre et Meuse” (ESEM). Activities included bird watching in the morning, botany in the afternoon, visit of natural preserves, a morning on moths and two nights on bats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One week discovering the wonders of Belgian nature!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/viroin2023.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/viroin2023.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New project MILANEOL to study mortality of the Red Kite by windmills</title><link href="/blog/MILANEOL/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New project MILANEOL to study mortality of the Red Kite by windmills" /><published>2023-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/MILANEOL</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/MILANEOL/">&lt;p&gt;Starting March 2023, we are studying the mortality of the Red Kite (Milvus milvus) by windmills. This project is funded by SPW (Wallonia public administration). It is a collaboration between University of Liège, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.csd.ch/fr/succursales/belgique/namur&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Natagora&lt;/a&gt;. The three main goals of the project are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Measure mortality via a search for corpses on the field in two windmill sites in Wallonia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Infer the viability of the population based on various growth scenarios in a statistical framework&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. From an ethics standpoint, study what an acceptable mortality is to justify a good conservation status&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arnaud Vansteenkiste, MSc, was hired for one year to conduct research on this project. Welcome Arnaud!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A collaboration between ULiège, CSD Ingénieurs and Natagora, funded by SPW</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/MILANEOL_pic.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/MILANEOL_pic.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Annual meeting of the French Association of Lichenology (2023)</title><link href="/blog/AFL_Elise_Fontainebleau/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Annual meeting of the French Association of Lichenology (2023)" /><published>2023-02-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/AFL_Elise_Fontainebleau</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/AFL_Elise_Fontainebleau/">&lt;p&gt;Created in 1976, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.afl-lichenologie.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;French Association of Lichenology (AFL)&lt;/a&gt; gathers people interested in lichens to determine them, to know their classification, their ecology, their role, their protection and their use...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFL facilitates exchanges between its members, as well as studies and work on lichens and promotes cooperation with foreign lichenologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AFL currently has about 300 members, both amateurs and professionals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each year, in February, a 4-day event is organized in the laboratories of the “Station d&apos;écologie forestière” in Fontainebleau city (near Paris). Each member brings the lichens that they are unable to determine and finds, with the other members, the help to progress in his determinations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expert lichenologists (Claude Roux, Chantal Van Haluwyn, Juliette Asta, Jean-Claude Boissière...) are generally present and conferences given in the evening allow new members to acquire knowledge and methodologies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elise Lebreton was invited to give a 30 min talk on her thesis project (first results). &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A week of meetings, work and conferences on french and french-overseas lichens !</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/20230223_152742.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/20230223_152742.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lichen Go in Liège for ‘Printemps des sciences’</title><link href="/blog/Lichengo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lichen Go in Liège for ‘Printemps des sciences’" /><published>2023-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Lichengo</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Lichengo/">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to collaborate with Prof. Yannick Agnan (Université Catholique de Louvain) for his project &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lichensgo.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lichen Go!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims at using citizen sciences tool to monitor lichens in Belgian cities and assess air quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An introduction and training by Prof. Agnan, with the assistance of members of our team, will be conducted in Liège on February 15th, in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rejouisciences.uliege.be/cms/c_17337457/fr/lichen-go-evaluez-la-qualite-de-l-air-dans-votre-quartier&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;More information can be found on the University website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A citizen science approach with lichens to monitor air quality</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/logo_lichensgo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/logo_lichensgo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Robert Lücking visits Liège !</title><link href="/blog/Robert/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Robert Lücking visits Liège !" /><published>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Robert</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Robert/">&lt;p&gt;As part of Elise’s thesis, Robert came to Liège from January 15 to 21 to work on the specimens collected during the two field missions (New Caledonia and Guadeloupe 2022). The work focused on lichens of the family Gomphillaceae. Robert also had the opportunity to give an intersting lecture on foliicolous lichens.
&lt;p&gt;Many discoveries have been made during this week and must now be published; Elise has a lot of work to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A very busy week for Elise, Emmanuël and Robert!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/robert.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/robert.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fieldtrip in New Caledonia for Elise’s thesis</title><link href="/blog/NouvelleCaledonie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fieldtrip in New Caledonia for Elise’s thesis" /><published>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/NouvelleCaledonie</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/NouvelleCaledonie/">&lt;p&gt;From October 30 to November 21, as a research collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iac.nc/bienvenue-a-l-iac/presentation/presentation-en-bref&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;New Caledonian Agronomic Institute (IAC)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.afl-lichenologie.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank_&quot;&gt;French Association of Lichenology (AFL)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patrinat.fr/fr&quot;&gt;UMS Patrinat (OFB/MNHN/CNRS)&lt;/a&gt;, Elise Lebreton (FRIA PhD Student) and Antoine Lespagnol (scientific collaborator) sampled lichens and leaves in Nouvelle Caledonie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Caledonia is one of the smallest biodiversity hotspots in the world. This territory is famous for its rich flora, with one of the highest endemism rates in the world (78.7% according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10531-021-02186-8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Véron et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;). Nevertheless, the knowledge about the fungal biodiversity of the archipelago is still fragmentary. We currently know only 10% of the Caledonian fungus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A part of the fungus concerns lichenized fungi (lichens). Among the lifestyle studied in lichens (growth on rocks, on tree bark etc...), foliicolous lichens (life cycle on tree leaves) had been poorly studied in New Caledonia until the collections of Kalb and Kalb (1994) on some localities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the field mission are:
&lt;p&gt;- To explore “Grande Terre” in order to find new locality with foliicolous lichens (other than what is already known)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Update the checklist of foliicolous lichens established by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283680017_New_Caledonia_foliicolous_lichens_and_island_biogeography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lücking &amp;amp; Kalb (2001)&lt;/a&gt; and continue the inventory of other lichens (microlichens, small opportunistic collections)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Use molecular tools on collected specimens to produce phylogeny of Gomphillaceae (family of lichens mainly foliicolous)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Caledonia is known for its bushy landscapes with red ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not the best place to find foliicolous lichens, which prefer preserved humid forests. Rainforest and cloud forest are not many left today because of deforestation. 
That&apos;s why it was sometimes necessary to drive and walk long hours to reach these environments.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;The field mission was a success with great contacts on site and thousands of interesting lichens to study in Liege !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So many lichens growing on leaves!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/nouvellecaledonie.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/nouvellecaledonie.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lucie goes to EUROLYNX 2022</title><link href="/blog/LucieEurolynx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lucie goes to EUROLYNX 2022" /><published>2022-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/LucieEurolynx</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/LucieEurolynx/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurolynx.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EUROLYNX&lt;/a&gt; is an open scientific network for collaborative science and data sharing on the ecology of the Eurasian lynx. Annual meetings are a valuable opportunity for its members to update on new projects, communicate on the scientific outputs, discuss ongoing scientific works and identify new lines of research. For its 4th edition, the EUROLYNX meeting took place in Eisenach, Germany, where Lucie had the opportunity to present her research on lynx dispersal and connectivity modeling around Belgium. There, she met lynx researchers from all over Europe and learned more about the functioning of the EUROLYNX network, while enjoying the very nice city of Eisenach. She will remember the friendly atmosphere and was very inspired by the sense of cohesive scientific community in this research group that has the common goal to improve wildlife management and conservation with scientific-driven decisions. One day maybe, Belgium will have its own lynx population and be part of this fantastic network!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The 4th Eurolynx meeting</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Lucie3.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Lucie3.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The lab goes to AMPEE</title><link href="/blog/AMPEE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The lab goes to AMPEE" /><published>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/AMPEE</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/AMPEE/">&lt;p&gt;On September 29th, 2022, Elise, Lea, Nicolas, Sébastien and Thibault went to the 6th AMPEE. AMPEE is an initiative of the Royal Botanical Society of Belgium and Meise Botanic Garden.
Our PhD students all presented their latest results, while Nicolas was quietly drinking coffee. Collaborator of the lab Luca Borgato also gave a talk. Looking forward to next year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">6th Annual Meeting on Plant Ecology and Evolution</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC</title><link href="/blog/Floramac/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC" /><published>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Floramac</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Floramac/">&lt;p&gt;FloraMac is a 5 days congress on the Macaronesian flora. Every three years it takes place in a different location with this year edition on the island of La Gomera, Canary Islands. Macaronesia is a group of four archipelagos: the Azores, Madeira, the Canary Islands and Cape Verde. &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mouton&quot;&gt;Lea Mouton&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mirolo&quot;&gt;Sébastien Mirolo&lt;/a&gt; were invited to present their current project about Beta diversity across geographic scales and lineages and about island disharmony and the origin of the Macaronesian bryophyte community, respectively. They had the opportunity to meet great researchers and learn more about the flora of islands and oceanic islands theories. In addition, they have been enjoying the beautiful landscape of this magnificent Canarian island. Because of its rich biodiversity and its high endemism rate, La Gomera was awarded Biosphere Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An International symposium on the Macaronesian flora</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lucie goes to BES Movement Ecology 2022</title><link href="/blog/LucieBESME/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lucie goes to BES Movement Ecology 2022" /><published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/LucieBESME</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/LucieBESME/">&lt;p&gt;The Movement Ecology Special Interest Group of the British Ecological Society hosted its first in person annual meeting on 7- 8 September 2022 at the University of Glasgow. This meeting took the theme of “Understanding animal movement in human-altered landscapes”. Lucie was invited to present the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://conscape.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ConScape&lt;/a&gt; software library (&lt;a href=&quot;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/2041-210X.13850&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Van Moorter et al., 2022&lt;/a&gt;) she is using for her connectivity analyses on Eurasian lynx dispersal in Central Europe. She had the chance to meet great researchers of her study field and deepen her knowledge of movement modeling. Great discussions on general issues with movement ecology and the effects of anthropogenic disturbance have arisen from these two meeting days, which ended up in an exciting project of grouped article on animal movement modeling in human-dominated landscapes to be published in 2023 in the BES journal. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The British Ecological Society Movement Ecology meeting</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Lucie2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Lucie2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>