<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-17T13:35:24+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BEC-ULiège</title><subtitle>Page of BEC-ULiège</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Margaux and Nicolas go to Zoology2024</title><link href="/blog/Zoology2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Margaux and Nicolas go to Zoology2024" /><published>2024-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Zoology2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Zoology2024/">&lt;p&gt;
On December 12-13, 2024, Margaux and Nicolas went to the Zoology 2024 meeting in Mons, Belgium. Margaux presented a poster describing her PhD project, studying the impact of urbanization on jackdaws, whereas Nicolas presented a poster with results of the MILANEOL project, estimating wind turbines mortality on Red Kites in Wallonia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Meeting by the Royal Belgian Zoological Society</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/zoology2024.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/zoology2024.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Margaux meets the corvid community of Vienna </title><link href="/blog/MargauxVienna/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Margaux meets the corvid community of Vienna " /><published>2024-10-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/MargauxVienna</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/MargauxVienna/">&lt;p&gt;
Invited by Thomas Bugnyar&apos;s lab, Margaux spent a week at the University of Vienna and the Konrad Lorenz Institute to learn more about the current studies made on wild and captive crows and raven, and meet all the scientists working on that topic.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Margaux goes to Austria</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/debug.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/debug.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Second field season for Margaux</title><link href="/blog/MargauxSecond/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Second field season for Margaux" /><published>2024-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/MargauxSecond</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/MargauxSecond/">&lt;p&gt;
From April until July, Margaux went collecting data for her PhD at the University of Exeter with the Cornish Jackdaw Project. She monitored the breeding season of wild jackdaws (Corvus monedula) and measured the risk-taking behaviour of female in comparison to the level of urbanisation our the nest. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Margaux goes to Cornwall</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Margaux2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Margaux2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Local TV talks about the project on Little Owl and Eurasian tree sparrow</title><link href="/blog/Cheveche/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local TV talks about the project on Little Owl and Eurasian tree sparrow" /><published>2024-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Cheveche</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Cheveche/">&lt;p&gt;Since 2023, BEC lab (Anne-Laure and Nicolas) collaborates with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pnbm.be/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Parc Naturel Burdinale-Mehaigne (PNBM)&lt;/a&gt; on a project to monitor Little Owl and Eurasian Tree Sparrow in the park, thanks to funding by SPW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our part of the project consists in studying the Little Owl through GPS tags to better understand how it uses the landscape. A master student, Clara Tirifahy, also works on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rtc.be/article/info/environnement/80-nichoirs-installes-dans-le-parc-naturel-burdinale-mehaigne_1517985_325.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Local TV came and interviewed Aurélie Decooman, who works on the project (in French)&lt;/a&gt;. A very nice piece!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Project led by PNBM</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/cheveche.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/cheveche.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Margaux gets the Herman Van Beneden prize!</title><link href="/blog/MargauxBeneden/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Margaux gets the Herman Van Beneden prize!" /><published>2024-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/MargauxBeneden</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/MargauxBeneden/">&lt;p&gt;Margaux, our new PhD student working in behavioural ecology has just received the Herman Van Beneden prize! This price will allow her to build the automated feeders necessary to study if the urbanisation level influences the cognitive flexibility abilities of the jackdaws during her fieldwork this Spring, in Cornwall (UK).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">To support her PhD project on jackdaws</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/MargauxBeneden.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/MargauxBeneden.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Open, Reproducible and Transparent Science in Ecology</title><link href="/blog/LucieOpen/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open, Reproducible and Transparent Science in Ecology" /><published>2023-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/LucieOpen</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/LucieOpen/">&lt;p&gt;Last November, Lucie headed to Hjerkinn (Norway) for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://open-science-course.github.io/course_website/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;one-week course on Open, Reproducible and Transparent Science in Ecology&lt;/a&gt;. Alongside experts from Living Norway, she gained new skills in open science, data management and standards (e.g. FAIR, CARE), and reproducible workflows. She was introduced to new methods, technologies, and open-source tools to producing more open, reproducible, and transparent research, as a way to improve the efficiency, quality and credibility of science. Now back in Belgium, she is eager to applying these skills in her own research and share them with colleagues. Of course, Lucie also took advantage of her time in Hjerkinn to learn more about reindeer management in Norway with a visit to the Wild Reindeer Centre and breathtaking hikes in the Dovre area reindeer call home!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One week in Norway for Lucie.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/lucieopen.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/lucieopen.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">AMPEE in Liège</title><link href="/blog/AMPEE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AMPEE in Liège" /><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/AMPEE</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/AMPEE/">&lt;p&gt;Every year, the Royal Botanical Society of Belgium organizes &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/ampee7/homepage&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AMPEE&lt;/a&gt; in Belgium. It is a 1-day scientific meeting that allows botanists from Belgium and abroad to share their research. It also allows PhD students and early-career scientists to present their work.
In 2023, it was organized in ULiège by Nicolas Magain and Annick Wilmotte. 
This year&apos;s meeting was entitled &quot;Small is beautiful, also in Botany&quot;, with a focus on algae, lichens and mosses.
The conference was a success, with 86 attendees, including 42 students. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Annual Meeting on Plant Ecology and Evolution</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field trip in Taiwan</title><link href="/blog/Taiwan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field trip in Taiwan" /><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Taiwan</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Taiwan/">&lt;p&gt;From November 18 to December 2, 2023, Alain and Nicolas participated in a 2-week field trip in Taiwan. This field trip was organized by Chen Ko-Hsuan and Huang Jen-Pan from Academia Sinica (Taipei, Taiwan). Their local colleagues and PhD students provided a great help to make this field trip a success. During this field trip, we collected mosses and lichens in the gorgeous forests and mountains of Taiwan. Our French colleague Romain Darnajoux was also part of the expedition.
A special focus was set on sampling a giant Cypress tree following an altitudinal gradient, as well as collecting foliicolous lichens, and cyanolichens. Thank you so much for everyone who contributed to this fantastic journey!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">With our partners at Academia Sinica</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Taiwan.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Taiwan.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field outings for BCBGs 2023!</title><link href="/blog/LeaBCBG/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field outings for BCBGs 2023!" /><published>2023-11-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/LeaBCBG</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/LeaBCBG/">&lt;p&gt;Nicolas and Lea manage the BCBG (Conservation Biology, Biodiversity and Management) master. As part of the courses, they brought their students to meet different stakeholders in nature conservation in Wallonia. This year, students had the opportunity to discover the life of an organic farmer, to interact with nature preserve managers and biologists involved in LIFE projects, PWDR, natural park or the Wolf plan. The students also visited a fish pass at the Lixhe dam, met a forest ranger/DNF agent and discovered different naturalist associations involved in the protection and preservation of biodiversity in Wallonia. This year the term ended at the Hortus press with a high-stem and Walloon apple juice. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Lea takes students everywhere!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/BCBG2023.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/BCBG2023.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">24 new Peltigera species!</title><link href="/blog/Persoonia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="24 new Peltigera species!" /><published>2023-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Persoonia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Persoonia/">&lt;p&gt;Published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/nhn/pimj/pre-prints/content-nbc-persoonia-0666&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Persoonia in August 2023&lt;/a&gt;, the long-awaited final paper of Nicolas&apos; thesis. It consists in a taxonomic revision of the Peltigera polydactylon section, with the description of 24 new species from all around the world.
In short, this clade mostly consists in species with specific biogeographic patterns and rather limited distributions, compared to the cosmopolitan taxa that they used to be considered as. Many colleagues from all over the world were involved, especially Jolanta Miadlikowska and François Luztoni from Duke University, and Bernard Goffinet from UCONN.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Nicolas finally publishes his PhD work!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Peltigera.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Peltigera.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>