<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-02-03T13:59:22+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BEC lab</title><subtitle>Page of BEC lab</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Lichen Go in Liège for ‘Printemps des sciences’</title><link href="/blog/Lichengo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lichen Go in Liège for ‘Printemps des sciences’" /><published>2023-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Lichengo</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Lichengo/">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to collaborate with Prof. Yannick Agnan (Université Catholique de Louvain) for his project &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lichensgo.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lichen Go!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims at using citizen sciences tool to monitor lichens in Belgian cities and assess air quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An introduction and training by Prof. Agnan, with the assistance of members of our team, will be conducted in Liège on February 15th, in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rejouisciences.uliege.be/cms/c_17337457/fr/lichen-go-evaluez-la-qualite-de-l-air-dans-votre-quartier&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;More information can be found on the University website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A citizen science approach with lichens to monitor air quality</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/logo_lichensgo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/logo_lichensgo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Robert Lücking visits Liège !</title><link href="/blog/Robert/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Robert Lücking visits Liège !" /><published>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Robert</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Robert/">&lt;p&gt;As part of Elise’s thesis, Robert came to Liège from January 15 to 21 to work on the specimens collected during the two field missions (New Caledonia and Guadeloupe 2022). The work focused on lichens of the family Gomphillaceae. Robert also had the opportunity to give an intersting lecture on foliicolous lichens.
&lt;p&gt;Many discoveries have been made during this week and must now be published; Elise has a lot of work to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A very busy week for Elise, Emmanuël and Robert!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/robert.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/robert.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fieldtrip in New Caledonia for Elise’s thesis</title><link href="/blog/NouvelleCaledonie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fieldtrip in New Caledonia for Elise’s thesis" /><published>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/NouvelleCaledonie</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/NouvelleCaledonie/">&lt;p&gt;From October 30 to November 21, as a research collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iac.nc/bienvenue-a-l-iac/presentation/presentation-en-bref&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;New Caledonian Agronomic Institute (IAC)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.afl-lichenologie.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank_&quot;&gt;French Association of Lichenology (AFL)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patrinat.fr/fr&quot;&gt;UMS Patrinat (OFB/MNHN/CNRS)&lt;/a&gt;, Elise Lebreton (FRIA PhD Student) and Antoine Lespagnol (scientific collaborator) sampled lichens and leaves in Nouvelle Caledonie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Caledonia is one of the smallest biodiversity hotspots in the world. This territory is famous for its rich flora, with one of the highest endemism rates in the world (78.7% according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10531-021-02186-8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Véron et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;). Nevertheless, the knowledge about the fungal biodiversity of the archipelago is still fragmentary. We currently know only 10% of the Caledonian fungus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A part of the fungus concerns lichenized fungi (lichens). Among the lifestyle studied in lichens (growth on rocks, on tree bark etc...), foliicolous lichens (life cycle on tree leaves) had been poorly studied in New Caledonia until the collections of Kalb and Kalb (1994) on some localities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the field mission are:
&lt;p&gt;- To explore “Grande Terre” in order to find new locality with foliicolous lichens (other than what is already known)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Update the checklist of foliicolous lichens established by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283680017_New_Caledonia_foliicolous_lichens_and_island_biogeography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lücking &amp;amp; Kalb (2001)&lt;/a&gt; and continue the inventory of other lichens (microlichens, small opportunistic collections)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Use molecular tools on collected specimens to produce phylogeny of Gomphillaceae (family of lichens mainly foliicolous)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Caledonia is known for its bushy landscapes with red ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not the best place to find foliicolous lichens, which prefer preserved humid forests. Rainforest and cloud forest are not many left today because of deforestation. 
That&apos;s why it was sometimes necessary to drive and walk long hours to reach these environments.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;The field mission was a success with great contacts on site and thousands of interesting lichens to study in Liege !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So many lichens growing on leaves!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/nouvellecaledonie.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/nouvellecaledonie.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The lab goes to AMPEE</title><link href="/blog/AMPEE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The lab goes to AMPEE" /><published>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/AMPEE</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/AMPEE/">&lt;p&gt;On September 29th, 2022, Elise, Lea, Nicolas, Sébastien and Thibault went to the 6th AMPEE. AMPEE is an initiative of the Royal Botanical Society of Belgium and Meise Botanic Garden.
Our PhD students all presented their latest results, while Nicolas was quietly drinking coffee. Collaborator of the lab Luca Borgato also gave a talk. Looking forward to next year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">6th Annual Meeting on Plant Ecology and Evolution</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC</title><link href="/blog/Floramac/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC" /><published>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Floramac</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Floramac/">&lt;p&gt;FloraMac is a 5 days congress on the Macaronesian flora. Every three years it takes place in a different location with this year edition on the island of La Gomera, Canary Islands. Macaronesia is a group of four archipelagos: the Azores, Madeira, the Canary Islands and Cape Verde. &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mouton&quot;&gt;Lea Mouton&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mirolo&quot;&gt;Sébastien Mirolo&lt;/a&gt; were invited to present their current project about Beta diversity across geographic scales and lineages and about island disharmony and the origin of the Macaronesian bryophyte community, respectively. They had the opportunity to meet great researchers and learn more about the flora of islands and oceanic islands theories. In addition, they have been enjoying the beautiful landscape of this magnificent Canarian island. Because of its rich biodiversity and its high endemism rate, La Gomera was awarded Biosphere Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An International symposium on the Macaronesian flora</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field course in Pyrenees</title><link href="/blog/Pyrenees/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field course in Pyrenees" /><published>2022-07-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Pyrenees</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Pyrenees/">&lt;p&gt;On July 3-13, 2022, students of the master in ecology and organisms biology (specialization in conservation biology) participated into a field course in Pyrenees (France and Spain) with &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/magain&quot;&gt;Nicolas Magain&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mouton&quot;&gt;Lea Mouton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Serusiaux&quot;&gt;Emmanuël Sérusiaux&lt;/a&gt;, Ludovic Sottiaux and Philippe Dury.
&lt;p&gt; We explored coexistence with big carnivorous animals such as wolves and bears, nature conservation and human impact on the landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the atlantic side in France to Bardenas in Aragon, students could observe so many organisms, including a lot of vultures and birds of prey, and relics from the Tertiary age such as  Ramonda myconi and carnivorous plants of the genus  Pinguicula).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few pictures are available on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CjhxGXejQ4v/&quot;&gt;Instagram page of the Faculty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Discovering nature, coexistence with bears and tropical relics</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pyrenees1.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/pyrenees1.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field course in Cevennes</title><link href="/blog/Cevennes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field course in Cevennes" /><published>2022-05-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Cevennes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Cevennes/">&lt;p&gt;On May 14-22, 2022, students of the master in ecology and organisms biology went to Cévennes (Lozère, France) for a field course in biogeography (&lt;a href=&quot;/members/Vanderpoorten&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alain Vanderpoorten&lt;/a&gt;) and plant systematics (&lt;a href=&quot;/members/magain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicolas Magain&lt;/a&gt;).

&lt;p&gt;Hosted in &quot;Camping de la cascade&quot; in Meyrueis, students enjoyed a perfect weather and discovered the landscapes of  Parc National des Cévennes.&lt;/p&gt;

&amp;lt;We studied the flora of very different landscapes, and discovered several endemic species, before doing some ecological modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some pictures can be found on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CisDKAljwVg/&quot;&gt;Instagram page of the Faculty.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ecological modelling and endemic species</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Cevennes8.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Cevennes8.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Antoine got a Marie Skłodowska-Curie postdoctoral fellowship!</title><link href="/blog/antoine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antoine got a Marie Skłodowska-Curie postdoctoral fellowship!" /><published>2022-03-30T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-03-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/antoine</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/antoine/">&lt;p&gt;Antoine Simon (post-doctoral fellow at UConn and BEC lab alumni) got awarded a Marie Skłodowska-Curie postdoctoral fellowship to work with Prof. Einar Timdal (Natural History Museum, University of Oslo) on genomic approaches applied to historical herbarium specimens. His project FRAME (Fungal Research in the Age of Museomic Exploration) will aim at generating informative genetic data from ancient lichen collections, providing a cost-effective and labor-saving strategy to integrate relevant museum collections in biodiversity research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Way to go Antoine! We are thrilled that we will continue collaborating with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Picture: Antoine posing on the southern New England tripoint marker, visibly thrilled to be simultaneously in Connecticut, Massachusetts and Rhode Island.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Great achievement for our former PhD student</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/antoine.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/antoine.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Collecting field trip in Parc National de Guadeloupe for Elise’s thesis</title><link href="/blog/guad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collecting field trip in Parc National de Guadeloupe for Elise’s thesis" /><published>2022-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/guad</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/guad/">&lt;p&gt;From January 18 to February 1st, as a research collaboration with the Parc National de Guadeloupe, Elise Lebreton (FRIA PhD Student), Nicolas Magain and Emmanuël Sérusiaux sampled lichens and leaves in Guadeloupe. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of organisms grow on the surface of leaves in tropical forests, including lichens, fungi, algae and bryophytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three main goals of the field trip were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- A taxonomic and phylogenetic revision of Gomphillaceae and Strigulaceae in Guadeloupe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Characterizing green algae within and outside of lichens at the surface of leaves from an ecological point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- A broader project of checklists of lichens from France&apos;s Overseas territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Even if recent sulphur emissions from the volcano seem to have harmed lichen communities, the field trip was a success, with many interesting specimens collected!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A lot of work for Elise in the lab now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; A slideshow of pictures from the field trip can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciences.uliege.be/cms/c_8984836/fr/mission-de-recolte-en-guadeloupe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Website of the Faculté des Sciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Picture: Barthélémy Dessanges from the Parc National de Guadeloupe delivering the collecting permits to Elise and Nicolas.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Two weeks collecting lichens and leaves</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/barthelemy.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/barthelemy.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lucie got a FRIA PhD fellowship!</title><link href="/blog/lucie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lucie got a FRIA PhD fellowship!" /><published>2021-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/lucie</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/lucie/">&lt;p&gt;Lucie Lelotte got a FRIA PhD fellowship!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucie obtained a FRIA fellowship from the FNRS to pursue 4 years of doctoral research in our lab, in collaboration with NINA (Norwegian Institute for Nature Research, the acronym must work in Norwegian).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She will be working on the spatial ecology, habitat selection and conservation biology of reindeers in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to joining our team, Lucie obtained a Master in Organisms Biology and Ecology with a specialisation in conservation biology (the infamous BCBG master, the acronym works in French) from Université de Liège. Her master thesis was already dedicated to Norwegian reindeers, in collaboration with Bram Van Moorter from NINA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations Lucie!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">FRIA fellowhsip to work on spatial ecology, habitat selection and conservation biology of reindeers in Norway</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Lucie.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Lucie.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>