<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-02-08T11:34:40+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BEC lab</title><subtitle>Page of BEC lab</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Lichen Go in Liège for ‘Printemps des sciences’</title><link href="/blog/Lichengo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lichen Go in Liège for ‘Printemps des sciences’" /><published>2023-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Lichengo</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Lichengo/">&lt;p&gt;We are happy to collaborate with Prof. Yannick Agnan (Université Catholique de Louvain) for his project &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lichensgo.eu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lichen Go!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims at using citizen sciences tool to monitor lichens in Belgian cities and assess air quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An introduction and training by Prof. Agnan, with the assistance of members of our team, will be conducted in Liège on February 15th, in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rejouisciences.uliege.be/cms/c_17337457/fr/lichen-go-evaluez-la-qualite-de-l-air-dans-votre-quartier&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;More information can be found on the University website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A citizen science approach with lichens to monitor air quality</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/logo_lichensgo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/logo_lichensgo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Robert Lücking visits Liège !</title><link href="/blog/Robert/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Robert Lücking visits Liège !" /><published>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Robert</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Robert/">&lt;p&gt;As part of Elise’s thesis, Robert came to Liège from January 15 to 21 to work on the specimens collected during the two field missions (New Caledonia and Guadeloupe 2022). The work focused on lichens of the family Gomphillaceae. Robert also had the opportunity to give an intersting lecture on foliicolous lichens.
&lt;p&gt;Many discoveries have been made during this week and must now be published; Elise has a lot of work to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A very busy week for Elise, Emmanuël and Robert!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/robert.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/robert.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fieldtrip in New Caledonia for Elise’s thesis</title><link href="/blog/NouvelleCaledonie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fieldtrip in New Caledonia for Elise’s thesis" /><published>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/NouvelleCaledonie</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/NouvelleCaledonie/">&lt;p&gt;From October 30 to November 21, as a research collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iac.nc/bienvenue-a-l-iac/presentation/presentation-en-bref&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;New Caledonian Agronomic Institute (IAC)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.afl-lichenologie.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank_&quot;&gt;French Association of Lichenology (AFL)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patrinat.fr/fr&quot;&gt;UMS Patrinat (OFB/MNHN/CNRS)&lt;/a&gt;, Elise Lebreton (FRIA PhD Student) and Antoine Lespagnol (scientific collaborator) sampled lichens and leaves in Nouvelle Caledonie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Caledonia is one of the smallest biodiversity hotspots in the world. This territory is famous for its rich flora, with one of the highest endemism rates in the world (78.7% according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10531-021-02186-8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Véron et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;). Nevertheless, the knowledge about the fungal biodiversity of the archipelago is still fragmentary. We currently know only 10% of the Caledonian fungus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A part of the fungus concerns lichenized fungi (lichens). Among the lifestyle studied in lichens (growth on rocks, on tree bark etc...), foliicolous lichens (life cycle on tree leaves) had been poorly studied in New Caledonia until the collections of Kalb and Kalb (1994) on some localities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the field mission are:
&lt;p&gt;- To explore “Grande Terre” in order to find new locality with foliicolous lichens (other than what is already known)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Update the checklist of foliicolous lichens established by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/283680017_New_Caledonia_foliicolous_lichens_and_island_biogeography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lücking &amp;amp; Kalb (2001)&lt;/a&gt; and continue the inventory of other lichens (microlichens, small opportunistic collections)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;- Use molecular tools on collected specimens to produce phylogeny of Gomphillaceae (family of lichens mainly foliicolous)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Caledonia is known for its bushy landscapes with red ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is not the best place to find foliicolous lichens, which prefer preserved humid forests. Rainforest and cloud forest are not many left today because of deforestation. 
That&apos;s why it was sometimes necessary to drive and walk long hours to reach these environments.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;The field mission was a success with great contacts on site and thousands of interesting lichens to study in Liege !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So many lichens growing on leaves!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/nouvellecaledonie.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/nouvellecaledonie.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lucie goes to EUROLYNX 2022</title><link href="/blog/LucieEurolynx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lucie goes to EUROLYNX 2022" /><published>2022-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/LucieEurolynx</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/LucieEurolynx/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eurolynx.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EUROLYNX&lt;/a&gt; is an open scientific network for collaborative science and data sharing on the ecology of the Eurasian lynx. Annual meetings are a valuable opportunity for its members to update on new projects, communicate on the scientific outputs, discuss ongoing scientific works and identify new lines of research. For its 4th edition, the EUROLYNX meeting took place in Eisenach, Germany, where Lucie had the opportunity to present her research on lynx dispersal and connectivity modeling around Belgium. There, she met lynx researchers from all over Europe and learned more about the functioning of the EUROLYNX network, while enjoying the very nice city of Eisenach. She will remember the friendly atmosphere and was very inspired by the sense of cohesive scientific community in this research group that has the common goal to improve wildlife management and conservation with scientific-driven decisions. One day maybe, Belgium will have its own lynx population and be part of this fantastic network!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The 4th Eurolynx meeting</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Lucie3.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Lucie3.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The lab goes to AMPEE</title><link href="/blog/AMPEE/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The lab goes to AMPEE" /><published>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/AMPEE</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/AMPEE/">&lt;p&gt;On September 29th, 2022, Elise, Lea, Nicolas, Sébastien and Thibault went to the 6th AMPEE. AMPEE is an initiative of the Royal Botanical Society of Belgium and Meise Botanic Garden.
Our PhD students all presented their latest results, while Nicolas was quietly drinking coffee. Collaborator of the lab Luca Borgato also gave a talk. Looking forward to next year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">6th Annual Meeting on Plant Ecology and Evolution</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/AMPEE.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC</title><link href="/blog/Floramac/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our PhD students go to FLORAMAC" /><published>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Floramac</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Floramac/">&lt;p&gt;FloraMac is a 5 days congress on the Macaronesian flora. Every three years it takes place in a different location with this year edition on the island of La Gomera, Canary Islands. Macaronesia is a group of four archipelagos: the Azores, Madeira, the Canary Islands and Cape Verde. &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mouton&quot;&gt;Lea Mouton&lt;/a&gt; and  &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mirolo&quot;&gt;Sébastien Mirolo&lt;/a&gt; were invited to present their current project about Beta diversity across geographic scales and lineages and about island disharmony and the origin of the Macaronesian bryophyte community, respectively. They had the opportunity to meet great researchers and learn more about the flora of islands and oceanic islands theories. In addition, they have been enjoying the beautiful landscape of this magnificent Canarian island. Because of its rich biodiversity and its high endemism rate, La Gomera was awarded Biosphere Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An International symposium on the Macaronesian flora</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/FLORAMAC.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lucie goes to BES Movement Ecology 2022</title><link href="/blog/LucieBESME/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lucie goes to BES Movement Ecology 2022" /><published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/LucieBESME</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/LucieBESME/">&lt;p&gt;The Movement Ecology Special Interest Group of the British Ecological Society hosted its first in person annual meeting on 7- 8 September 2022 at the University of Glasgow. This meeting took the theme of “Understanding animal movement in human-altered landscapes”. Lucie was invited to present the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://conscape.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ConScape&lt;/a&gt; software library (&lt;a href=&quot;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/2041-210X.13850&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Van Moorter et al., 2022&lt;/a&gt;) she is using for her connectivity analyses on Eurasian lynx dispersal in Central Europe. She had the chance to meet great researchers of her study field and deepen her knowledge of movement modeling. Great discussions on general issues with movement ecology and the effects of anthropogenic disturbance have arisen from these two meeting days, which ended up in an exciting project of grouped article on animal movement modeling in human-dominated landscapes to be published in 2023 in the BES journal. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The British Ecological Society Movement Ecology meeting</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Lucie2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Lucie2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lucie goes to ECCB 2022</title><link href="/blog/LucieECCB/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lucie goes to ECCB 2022" /><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/LucieECCB</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/LucieECCB/">&lt;p&gt;The 6th edition of the European Congress of Conservation Biology was held in Prague, Czech Republic on the theme “Biodiversity crisis in a changing world”. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one week, practitioners, consultants, politicians, conservation and social scientists were welcomed at the Czech University of Life Sciences to discuss and design new guidelines, tools and strategies in order to meet new challenges in times of biodiversity crisis. In a scientific program featuring dozens of plenaries, symposia, workshops, contributed talks and posters, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bec-lab.github.io/members/Lelotte/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lucie&lt;/a&gt; had the chance to present her work on Habitat selection modeling to assess drivers of habitat loss in wild reindeer. She enjoyed meeting researchers from all around the world, discussing conservation in an international context and discovering Prague! The ECCB 2022 was a very inspiring experience for Lucie as a PhD student and will, for sure, remain one of the highlights of her doctoral program.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The 6th European Congress of Conservation Biology</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Lucie1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Lucie1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field course in Pyrenees</title><link href="/blog/Pyrenees/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field course in Pyrenees" /><published>2022-07-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-07-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Pyrenees</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Pyrenees/">&lt;p&gt;On July 3-13, 2022, students of the master in ecology and organisms biology (specialization in conservation biology) participated into a field course in Pyrenees (France and Spain) with &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/magain&quot;&gt;Nicolas Magain&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Mouton&quot;&gt;Lea Mouton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;/members/Serusiaux&quot;&gt;Emmanuël Sérusiaux&lt;/a&gt;, Ludovic Sottiaux and Philippe Dury.
&lt;p&gt; We explored coexistence with big carnivorous animals such as wolves and bears, nature conservation and human impact on the landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the atlantic side in France to Bardenas in Aragon, students could observe so many organisms, including a lot of vultures and birds of prey, and relics from the Tertiary age such as  Ramonda myconi and carnivorous plants of the genus  Pinguicula).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few pictures are available on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CjhxGXejQ4v/&quot;&gt;Instagram page of the Faculty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Discovering nature, coexistence with bears and tropical relics</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/pyrenees1.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/pyrenees1.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Field course in Cevennes</title><link href="/blog/Cevennes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Field course in Cevennes" /><published>2022-05-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/Cevennes</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Cevennes/">&lt;p&gt;On May 14-22, 2022, students of the master in ecology and organisms biology went to Cévennes (Lozère, France) for a field course in biogeography (&lt;a href=&quot;/members/Vanderpoorten&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alain Vanderpoorten&lt;/a&gt;) and plant systematics (&lt;a href=&quot;/members/magain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicolas Magain&lt;/a&gt;).

&lt;p&gt;Hosted in &quot;Camping de la cascade&quot; in Meyrueis, students enjoyed a perfect weather and discovered the landscapes of  Parc National des Cévennes.&lt;/p&gt;

&amp;lt;We studied the flora of very different landscapes, and discovered several endemic species, before doing some ecological modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some pictures can be found on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/p/CisDKAljwVg/&quot;&gt;Instagram page of the Faculty.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ecological modelling and endemic species</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Cevennes8.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Cevennes8.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>