<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-18T17:36:58+02:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BEC-ULiège</title><subtitle>Page of BEC-ULiège</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Working on a management plan for raccoons in Wallonia</title><link href="/blog/raccoon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Working on a management plan for raccoons in Wallonia" /><published>2025-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/raccoon</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/raccoon/">&lt;p&gt;The team of Nicolas magain, in collaboration with Prof. Dorothée Denayer &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seed.uliege.be/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(SEED-ULiège)&lt;/a&gt;, is working on a management plan for raccoons in Wallonia. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new researcher, Eva Tafforeau, is going to work on this project for one year in our team. Welcome Eva! Another researcher, Pauline Emond, will work on the project in the SEED team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is a close collaboration with SPW ARNE, which funds the project, as well as with DEMNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raccoons are an invasive alien species which is suspected to threaten a lot of indigenous species, including endangered birds and amphibians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great challenge, and a very exciting transdisciplinary project with a team of biologists and social scientists. We will try to better understand the impact of raccoons on species and habitats in Wallonia, and to work on several scenarios of management. We will also meet and discuss with all stakeholders involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">New project on this invasive alien species</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/raccoon.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/raccoon.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Margaux and Nicolas go to Zoology2024</title><link href="/blog/Zoology2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Margaux and Nicolas go to Zoology2024" /><published>2024-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Zoology2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Zoology2024/">&lt;p&gt;
On December 12-13, 2024, Margaux and Nicolas went to the Zoology 2024 meeting in Mons, Belgium. Margaux presented a poster describing her PhD project, studying the impact of urbanization on jackdaws, whereas Nicolas presented a poster with results of the MILANEOL project, estimating wind turbines mortality on Red Kites in Wallonia.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Meeting by the Royal Belgian Zoological Society</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/zoology2024.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/zoology2024.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GuaCaMol project – Microclimate of the laurel forest</title><link href="/blog/Guacamol/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GuaCaMol project – Microclimate of the laurel forest" /><published>2024-12-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Guacamol</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Guacamol/">&lt;p&gt;
From December 7 to 14, a part of our team went to Tenerife as part of Sébastien’s PhD thesis and our new student Clara’s master thesis. For 6 days, they placed climatic sensors in different parts of the best preserved locations of the laurel forest endemic to Macaronesia. The goal is to determine the buffering effect of the canopy and to infer the difference between macro and microclimate. Jairo Patiño, Sébastien’s supervisor from the University of La Laguna (ULL), joined our team for fieldwork in the Natural Reserve of Anaga.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">With Sébastien and Clara</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Guacamol.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Guacamol.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The EPIFOR project comes to an end </title><link href="/blog/Epifor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The EPIFOR project comes to an end " /><published>2024-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/Epifor</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/Epifor/">&lt;p&gt;
The EPIFOR project started in March 2023. The project was financed by the SPW (Walloon Public Administration) and it was a collaboration between the University of Louvain-la-Neuve, the University of Liège and Epiphytia. The aim of the EPIFOR project was to identify bryophyte and lichen indicator species for the continuity and naturalness of forests in Wallonia, and then to propose advice to forest managers to improve the quality of Walloon forests in terms of continuity and naturalness. Alain Vanderpoorten, Lea Mouton and Virginie Hustemekers found 15 epiphytic bryophytes that indicate three levels of continuity and naturalness in a forest. 
Dicranum scoparium, Homalothecium sericeum, Isothecium alopecuroides, Isothecium myosuroides, Orthotrichum stramineum, Ulota crispa, Zygodon sp. indicate a good level of naturalness in the forests. These forest patches are ideal for the creation of islands of aging.
If Frullania tamarisci, Leucodon sciuroides, Metzgeria temperata/violacea, Microlejeunea ulicina and/or Neckera sp. are found in a forest, the forest indicates a high level of continuity and naturalness. An island of senescence could be created locally to preserve sensitive species and restore the special connectivity of the forest. 
In the presence of Antitrichia curtipendula, Blepharostoma trichophyllum and/or Ptilidium pulcherrimum, which are patrimonial species and which indicate a very high level of continuity and naturalness, the forest should be classified to integral reserve to preserve the quality of the forest.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">SPW project on epiphyte mosses</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/EPIFOR2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/EPIFOR2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A new Bryo Team</title><link href="/blog/BryoLunch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new Bryo Team" /><published>2024-11-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-11-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/BryoLunch</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/BryoLunch/">&lt;p&gt;
With the arrival of 5 new PhD students working on bryophytes, Alain organizes a bryo-lunch once a week to teach bryophyte identification to his PhD students. Jules, Alix, Adèle, Kelly, Tim and Lea have started with the Pleurocarps species found in the forest around the university. For the time being, they are able to identify 6 large families of pleurocarps with and without vein. Alain teaches the students first in the field using macro-identification criteria and then in the laboratory using microscopic and cellular criteria.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">5 new PhD students working with Alain</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Bryolunch.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Bryolunch.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Margaux meets the corvid community of Vienna </title><link href="/blog/MargauxVienna/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Margaux meets the corvid community of Vienna " /><published>2024-10-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/MargauxVienna</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/MargauxVienna/">&lt;p&gt;
Invited by Thomas Bugnyar&apos;s lab, Margaux spent a week at the University of Vienna and the Konrad Lorenz Institute to learn more about the current studies made on wild and captive crows and raven, and meet all the scientists working on that topic.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Margaux goes to Austria</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/debug.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/debug.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mushroom excursion in Ardenne after IMC</title><link href="/blog/IMC_mushroom_excursion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mushroom excursion in Ardenne after IMC" /><published>2024-08-17T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/IMC_mushroom_excursion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/IMC_mushroom_excursion/">&lt;p&gt;
The International Mycological Congress (IMC) was organized in Maastricht (Netherlands) on August 12-15, 2024. Nicolas helped Vincent Demoulin organize organize a one-day field trip in Belgium (mostly Ardenne) with the Botanical Society of Liège. It was a very rainy day! Highlights included visiting the collecting sites of Darrimont in Biron, and Battle of the Bulge hills in Bastogne. Thanks to Tatiana San Juan for the picture!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">With the Botanical Society of Liège</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/IMCmushroom.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/IMCmushroom.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lichen excursion after the IMC meeting</title><link href="/blog/IMC_excursion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lichen excursion after the IMC meeting" /><published>2024-08-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-08-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/IMC_excursion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/IMC_excursion/">&lt;p&gt;
The International Mycological Congress (IMC) was organized in Maastricht (Netherlands) on August 12-15, 2024. Nicolas organized a post-conference excursion close to Lissingen in Eiffel, Germany. He was helped by Emmanuël, Elise, Damien Ertz and Alain Demoulin. About 50 lichenologists and lichen enthusiasts attended this field day. Highlights included Lobaria amplissima, Peltigera lepidophora and Peltigera malacea. We also learnt a lot of facts about the volcano activity int he region. Thanks to Manuela Dal Forno for the picture!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In Eiffel, Germany</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/excursionIMC.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/excursionIMC.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Lea and Sébastien go to IBC</title><link href="/blog/IBC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lea and Sébastien go to IBC" /><published>2024-07-28T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-07-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/IBC</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/IBC/">&lt;p&gt;
Two of our PhD students, Lea and Sébastien, took part in the twentieth edition of the International Botanical Congress (or IBC XX), organized in Madrid from July 21 to 28. Lea gave a talk to present her last results about the new drivers of the epiphytic bryophytes, namely the fine particulate matter (PM2.5 and PM10) present in the air. During the congress, she also met the international community of bryologists, notably at the IAB’s meeting (International Association of Bryologists). Sébastien presented his final results about the Macaronesian bryophyte flora and its origins. He was able to meet with his colleagues from the University of La Laguna where he is also working and start new collaborations.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">International Botanical Congress in Madrid</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/IBC.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/IBC.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Second field season for Margaux</title><link href="/blog/MargauxSecond/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Second field season for Margaux" /><published>2024-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/blog/MargauxSecond</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/MargauxSecond/">&lt;p&gt;
From April until July, Margaux went collecting data for her PhD at the University of Exeter with the Cornish Jackdaw Project. She monitored the breeding season of wild jackdaws (Corvus monedula) and measured the risk-taking behaviour of female in comparison to the level of urbanisation our the nest. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Margaux goes to Cornwall</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/images/Margaux2.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/images/Margaux2.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>